<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to the misrepresenter of papists being a vindication of that part of the Protestant preface to the Wholesome advices from the Blessed Virgin, &amp;c. which concerns the Protestants charity to papists, and a layman's writing it : in answer to what is objected against it in the 4th chapter of the second part of the Papist misrepresented, &amp;c. / by the same layman who translated the Wholesome advices, &amp;c. and made the preface to them.</title>
            <author>Taylor, James, fl. 1687-1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63629</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39707</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18473803</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18473803</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107793</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63629)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107793)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1644:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to the misrepresenter of papists being a vindication of that part of the Protestant preface to the Wholesome advices from the Blessed Virgin, &amp;c. which concerns the Protestants charity to papists, and a layman's writing it : in answer to what is objected against it in the 4th chapter of the second part of the Papist misrepresented, &amp;c. / by the same layman who translated the Wholesome advices, &amp;c. and made the preface to them.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, James, fl. 1687-1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.D. for J. Robinson ... and Thomas Newborough ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Jan. 14. 1686. Imprimatur, Guil, Needham."</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Taylor by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  Papist misrepresented and represented. --  Second part.</term>
               <term>Widenfeldt, Adam, 1617 or 18-1678. --  Monita salutaria B.V. Mariae ad cultores suos indiscretos. --  English.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107793:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107793:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER TO THE Miſrepreſenter of Papiſts. BEING A Vindication of that part of the Proteſtant Preface to the <hi>Wholeſome Advices from the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin,</hi> &amp;c. which concerns the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Charity to <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and a Layman's writing it.</p>
            <p>IN Anſwer to what is Objected againſt it in the 4th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Second Part of the <hi>Papiſt Miſrepreſented,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By the ſame <hi>LAYMAN</hi> who tranſlated the <hi>Wholeſome Advices,</hi> &amp;c. and made the Preface to them.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Guil. Needham.</signed>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Jan.</hi> 14. 1686.</date>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. D.</hi> for <hi>J. Robinſon</hi> at the Golden Lion, and <hi>Thomas Newborough</hi> at the Star in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:107793:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107793:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>LETTER</hi> to the Miſrepreſenter of PAPISTS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Find that the Tranſlation of the <hi>Wholſom Advices from the Bleſſed Virgin, &amp;c.</hi> which may have help'd to ſettle the Minds of others, has ſomething diſcompos'd yours. For tho you are not, I dare ſay, pleas'd with the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Preface</hi> to it, yet however you diſſemble your pain. Wiſe-men ſay that you bite that <hi>Preface</hi> for grief of the <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation.</hi> I cannot but admire the Art of you Gentlemen of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in running down Books with bold Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, which you know not otherwiſe how to deal with. This <hi>Tranſlation</hi> and <hi>Preface,</hi> for ſome Reaſons, is an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore to you; and chiefly for helping to ſpoil the new Faſhion of maintaining <hi>Popery</hi> by <hi>Repreſenting</hi> it. Something there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be done with it; and ſo a little part of the <hi>Preface,</hi> which did not belong neither to the main deſign of the Book, muſt be ſingled out and be made an Example. As for all the reſt, 'tis ſufficiently anſwer'd by ſaying, <hi>Muſt I ſet up for Reader of Anatomy upon all the Pamphlets that come into the World? I am highly obliged to you for the Kindneſs; but I think the Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger has much the better Office, who his nothing but Dirt and Sinks to deal with, much leſs offenſive, than to be always raking into filthy Calumnies, fulſome Incongruities, and noyſom Impertinencies.</hi> Which kind of Language one would hardly uſe, but out of a great deſire to be unanſwerable one way or other. After this touch upon the whole, you come to <hi>touch at ſome particulars which ſeem to fall within your Province of Repreſenting;</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to touch at ſomething, which you were the better provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to touch, becauſe you had in the very ſame manner touch it before in your <hi>fourth Vindication of the Firſt Part.</hi> The particular is, That <hi>Papiſts</hi> allow no leſs a <hi>poſſibility</hi> of Salvation to <hi>Proteſtants</hi> than <hi>Proteſtants</hi> do to <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Now
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107793:3"/>altho this is all that I am concern'd to oppoſe; yet I ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a few words to your Preparatory Diſcourſe, in which you pretend to ſhew what good reaſon you have to pronounce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of Salvation amongſt us; or rather in the new faſhion'd Phraſe, that we as Proteſtants are guilty of <hi>Sins inconſiſtent with Salvation,</hi> inasmuch as we are ſeparated from your Communion. The ſhort of what you ſay is, <hi>That after moſt ſerious conſiderations and the weighing of all reaſons,</hi> the <hi>Papiſt</hi> believes the <hi>Roman</hi> Church <hi>in which he is, to be</hi> that one only holy Catholick Church, and therefore he <hi>does not queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but what is truly affirm'd of the Church of the Apoſtles and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages, and thoſe that fell from it, is moſt true of the ſame Church now in being, of which he is a Member, and of all thoſe who ſeparate from it, upon what pretext ſoever.</hi> Now it had been much more to the purpoſe to have produced thoſe ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Conſiderations, than to have ſpent ſo much time as you did, to prove what none of us make the leaſt queſtion of, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt Eſtabliſh'd a Catholick Church; that he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Care of it to the Apoſtles; that they were inſpir'd with the knowledg of Truth; that they left Paſtors to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern and feed the Flock after their deceaſe; and that the Promiſe of Salvation is made to Believers, excluſively to Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers. This I ſay is all very true, but not to your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, unleſs you had prov'd alſo, what you do but inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, <hi>That we have ſeparated our ſelves from the Doctrine and Government of the Church of Chriſt.</hi> Which words I wonder that you were not afraid to uſe, when they lay ſo fair to be turn'd upon your ſelves. For we are no leſs ſure, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of your Doctrines are no parts of the Doctrine of <hi>that</hi> Church; and that <hi>Rome</hi>'s being the Mother and Miſtreſs of all Churches, was not the Government of <hi>that</hi> Church over which the Apoſtles were, <hi>&amp;c. Overſeers</hi> for their time, than we are that ſuch a Church was eſtabliſhed in the World. And therefore if they who ſeparate themſelves from <hi>the Doctrine and Government of the Church of Chriſt,</hi> as it was firſt eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd, cannot hope for Salvation: Pray look to your ſelves as to that Point, inſtead of contending that you are the <hi>only, Catholick</hi> Church, out of which there is no hope of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:107793:3"/>
            <p>As to what you would inſinuate, that there muſt be in the Church a Succeſſion of Paſtors to the Worlds end, who ſhould no more err in teaching, than the Apoſtles themſelves did, and that your Church has that Succeſſion. I muſt tell you as to the firſt, that it is by no means prov'd from <hi>John</hi> 14. <hi>v.</hi> 16. ſince what is there promis'd to the Apoſtles, is not promis'd to the Church of all Ages, ſo as it was to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. The Spirit of God abode with the Apoſtles for ever, that is, ſo long as they liv'd, to guide them into the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Truth, and by them to guide the Church in all after-Ages. There are many things in this Diſcourſe of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to his Apoſtles, which cannot be apply'd to any Age of the Church after theirs. And therefore what is, and what is not limited to them, muſt be argued out from the Nature of the things themſelves which are ſaid. And laſtly, tho you will not have this Promiſe limited to the Perſons of the Apoſtles, but annext to their Function, as in ſome ſenſe I grant it may be; yet you ought to have taken notice, that the Promiſe is however limited by a Condition, even in the words foregoing and following the Promiſe; <hi>If ye love me, keep my Commandments,</hi> and there the Condition is once ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt. For it follows, <hi>And I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever, even the Spirit of Truth.</hi> And now mark once again what follows, <hi>Whom the World cannot receive, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him.</hi> Where, if by the <hi>World,</hi> be meant worldly and wicked Men, as I believe you will grant; you ſee here is no abſolute promiſe of ſuch a Guidance to a Succeſſion of Paſtors, as ſhall make it at any time of the Church <hi>Hereſy</hi> to contradict whatſoever they teach, or <hi>Schiſm</hi> to withdraw from their Obedience. As to the laſt; If you had prov'd ſuch a Succeſſion of Infallible Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers as you ſpeak of; yet I tell you once more, that the hardeſt part of your Task would be ſtill behind; which is to prove, That you have had all along, and ſtill have that Succeſſion; which I deſire you to do in your next, if you can, if it be but for the Inſtruction of a <hi>Layman</hi> that deſires to be led into all Truth, neceſſary, or even profitable for his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. And becauſe I would not have you loſe your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, I will open my greateſt Difficulty againſt this belief.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107793:4"/>I am ſure you cannot go about this Work without taking Scripture in to furniſh out your Argument. Now I deſire you to bring me ſuch Scriptures, which ſhall at leaſt make it as evident, that your Church was always to have a Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Infallible Teachers, as it is to me from divers other Scriptures evident, that your Paſtors have moſt certainly contradicted the Doctrine of the Scriptures. And when you have done this, you ſhall hear farther from me. In the mean time, your looſe Affirmations concerning the Catholick Church have been ſo often anſwered, that you need not wonder that a Layman of our Church can tell what to ſay to them.</p>
            <p>But to come to that wherein I am particularly concern'd. You are diſturb'd at my ſaying, <hi>That the Worſhip, Doctrines and Practices of the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>are ſo extreamly dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, that nothing but Invincible Ignorance, of which God only can judg, can give us any reaſonable hopes of their Salvation who live and die in that Communion.</hi> Now ſurely the uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of this does not lie in ſuppoſing that <hi>Invincible Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> will be pleadable in this Caſe, for 'tis a Plea which will go a great way amongſt thoſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion: which, I ſay, with the more confidence, becauſe in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Countries where I have been, the People ſeem to me to have the faireſt claim to the benefit of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> that can be well imagin'd amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Now ſince at laſt you are brought in this Pamphlet of yours to agree with Proteſtants, that <hi>Ignorance</hi> will ſave Men, and that we yield the greateſt part of the People have an indiſputable right to it; are not the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable to a high degree? If this will not pleaſe you, I do not know what will. Surely, Sir, you do not expect that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhould believe and ſay, that you, with all your Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors about you, are in as ſafe a way to Salvation, as they themſelves who have renounced them? If this could be, what, I pray ye, made our Fore-fathers ſuffer themſelves to be ſeparated from your Communion? or makes us that we cannot join with you? Certainly this was, and is ſtill nothing but want of ſound Faith, purity of Doctrines and Worſhip. And I know nothing elſe can, or ever was pretended to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy our Separation. And this alone one would think might be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107793:4"/>ſufficient to vindicate my Aſſertion from being <hi>uncharitable.</hi> But perhaps I may do it more by and by.</p>
            <p>But you'l tell me that nevertheleſs <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are <hi>as</hi> uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and come not <hi>an Ace</hi> behind them. Indeed I ſhould be very ſorry this were true. And tho it is, I know, an untoward Queſtion <hi>to Papiſts,</hi> yet I muſt ask, How do you prove this, Sir? Why thus. <hi>Proteſtants</hi> only allow Salvation to <hi>Papiſts</hi> upon Invincible Ignorance, and <hi>Papiſts</hi> do the ſame to <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> I muſt confeſs that in this Paper of yours, you grant Salvation to <hi>Proteſtants who live piouſly, and repent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely of all offences, and through invincible Ignorance remain in that Communion.</hi> Now whatever Truth there is in the Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf, yet from you we look upon this Conceſſion as a piece of <hi>New</hi> Popery. The <hi>Old</hi> Popery was, <hi>Proteſtancy unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of Damns.</hi> Neither <hi>Invincible Ignorance,</hi> nor <hi>Piety,</hi> nor any <hi>Repentance</hi> that included not a leaving the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> Communion, and joining with the <hi>Romiſh,</hi> could Save. But here we take notice, that of this, as well as of all the other unreaſonable pieces of <hi>Old</hi> Popery, you begin at laſt to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd, or at leaſt to think it for the Intereſt of your deſign on foot, to <hi>deny</hi> them, or diſguiſe and ſoften them, that ſo they may go the better down with thoſe People who are not ſo well read in your Controverſies, and ſuſpect no Snake in the Graſs. But to go on with my Point. Did not the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>Charity Miſtaken</hi> and <hi>Charity Maintain'd</hi> (which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd that <hi>incomparable</hi> Book of Mr.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Charity main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi>'d. P. 1. c. 7. Sect. 6. <hi>and in divers other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of that, and Charity Miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chillingworth</hi>) ſtifly and boldly aſſert, <hi>That all Roman Catholicks, not one excepted,</hi> — Do with unanimous conſent believe and profeſs that Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy unrepented deſtroys Salvation? Did not the Jeſuite, in his Relation of Bp. <hi>Laud</hi>'s Conference<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſwear upon his <hi>Soul, That there was but one ſaving Faith, and that is the Roman?</hi> And now in our Days, has not a
<note n="*" place="margin">Lucilla <hi>and</hi> Elizabeth.</note> Late Paper endeavour'd to make us as great <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> as the <hi>Donatiſts?</hi> And according to you, can <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> dying ſuch, go to Heaven? And does not that Author force St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to tell us in plain terms, <hi>That whoſoever is ſeparated from the Catholick Church</hi> (by which, againſt all Modeſty and Truth, you always mean your own <hi>particular</hi> Church) <hi>how laudably ſoever he thinks himſelf to live, for this only Crime,</hi> that he is disjoin'd from the Unity of Chriſt (that is to ſay, in your Language, the Pope) <hi>he ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107793:5"/>not have Life, but the Wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> Pray, Sir, be ſo kind, if not to me, yet to your ſelf, to reconcile theſe Sayings with what you ſay, viz. <hi>That there is no Papiſts but what will grant ſuch Proteſtants hopes of Salvation, who living pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and repenting ſincerely of all Offences, and through invincible Ignorance remain in that Communion.</hi> Where's the Truth and Honeſty now of your Aſſertion, That there is <hi>No Papiſt, &amp;c.?</hi> When I have already produced three, and perhaps if I pleas'd, could name three hundred. What do you call this amongſt you? We call it contradicting one another. Well, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever pray obſerve here's two ſorts of Popery. But which muſt a Man rely on for Orthodox? The <hi>Old,</hi> or the <hi>New</hi> Popery. I muſt confeſs I am inclin'd to believe the <hi>New</hi> to be beſt, but certainly the <hi>Old</hi> Popery is the true ſtanding Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But ſuppoſe we ſtood in need of the <hi>New,</hi> what ſhould we be the better for't, unleſs the Conceſſion were ſtampt with the <hi>Fiſhers</hi> Seal? for you that deal it out to the World, are but a private obſcure Man, and your Church is no more bound to ſtand to what you ſay, than mine is to what I ſay, unleſs it be Truth. This that you grant, at beſt, is but a ſign, that you have a better opinion of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion than the Generality of your Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But to let this paſs. I will now prove this Truth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond any poſſible Reply, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Papiſts</hi> deny Salvation to <hi>Proteſtants</hi> remaining <hi>ſuch,</hi> and that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> grant a <hi>Poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> of it to <hi>Papiſts</hi> remaining <hi>ſuch:</hi> And therefore by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, the <hi>firſt</hi> muſt needs be on the <hi>uncharitable,</hi> and the <hi>laſt</hi> on the <hi>charitable</hi> ſide. And this I ſhall do by ſhewing, that <hi>our</hi> Charity is ſo great to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>their</hi> want of it ſo apparent to us, that they have abus'd it into an Argument againſt us. And this is ſo notoriouſly true, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are not aſham'd to boaſt of it in their Writings and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; thinking thereby to draw weak Perſons, that cannot conſider where the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at of the Argument lies to be of <hi>their</hi> Church: And with this deceitful Argument, which they have fram'd from <hi>our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rity to them, and <hi>their want</hi> of it to us, I have heard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> make a great noiſe, and tell of the mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hty Feats it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. But certainly it was amongſt ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had thrown away all their <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Senſe;</hi> or elſe if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> been no other thing to recommend the Church of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107793:5"/>
               <hi>England,</hi> they would have thought that to be the beſt and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Church, which eminently has the very Beauty and Form of Chriſtian Religion, <hi>viz. Charity,</hi> which the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſo conſtantly and largely maintains and practiſes. But the Argument is this,—<hi>You Proteſtants confeſs Salvation May be had in the Romiſh Church, but we Papiſts utterly deny it to yours; therefore by the Confeſſion of both ſides, thoſe that are in our Church are ſafe; but there is great queſtion concerning</hi> Proteſtants, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſuch, for none but themſelves ſay they can be ſaved.</hi> What think you now, Sir, of the <hi>Proteſtants Charity,</hi> and the <hi>Papiſts want of it?</hi> Is here any proviſion made for poor <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> by <hi>Invincible Ignorance?</hi> If this does not prove that <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> have <hi>ſome</hi> Charity for <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>they none</hi> at all for us <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> I do not know what can. And that you could be ignorant of theſe things, and this Argument ſo commonly us'd by your Men, when they would deceive the well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People of our Church, you muſt excuſe me if I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it. With what Face then, Sir, could you tell the <hi>gaping multitude,</hi> as you think fit to call the poor honeſt People, <hi>That Papiſts do not advance the Damnation of Proteſtants one Ace farther againſt them, than the Proteſtants againſt Papiſts; and that the Doctrine of Proteſtants in this affair is the ſame in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to each other; and the Proteſtants are as uncharitable Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Papiſts as they are made to be of the Proteſtants?</hi> And now the matter being brought to this iſſue; Pray, Sir, tell me who are the <hi>uncharitable Damners, thunderers of Hell and Damnation! who impoſes upon the People? who are the injurious Slanderers? And who is it that render the Papiſts black and odions for their uncharitableneſs,</hi> but the Papiſts themſelves? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, Sir, if <hi>your Eye-ſight had not been horribly indiſpos'd with the malignant Influence of Rome,</hi> you would have ſeen, that the <hi>unchriſtian Damners</hi> are the <hi>Papiſts only.</hi> For ſhame learn, tho late, to maintain your Cauſe by <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> or let it periſh.</p>
            <p>But I foreſee that you may take it a little ill, that our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity extends not to the <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Judicious,</hi> in the number of which I dare ſay you reckon your ſelf. Now for theſe Perſons we are to conſider, whether they know or believe ſuch and ſuch things to be falſe, which yet for <hi>Worldly</hi> Ends they maintain for Truths; or after an honeſt diligent ſearch,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107793:6"/>cannot by any means diſcover them to be Errors, hindred by prepoſſeſſion, Education, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For theſe laſt Perſons I cannot ſee why <hi>Invincible Ignorance</hi> will not comprehend them as well as the ordinary and unlearned People: For I cannot tell what Invincible Ignorance is, unleſs it be this, <hi>That after all our beſt endeavours according to our utmoſt ability and means, we yet cannot diſcern which is Error, and which is Truth.</hi> But now for the firſt ſort, who maintain known <hi>Errors</hi> for <hi>Truths,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Conſcience, only for <hi>Secular</hi> Advantages (in the number of which I pray God you be not) what would you have us believe or ſay of them? <hi>God Almighty</hi> Himſelf has made no Proviſion, that we know of, for bold, wilful and impenitent Sinners. We <hi>judg no Man that hath a Maſter to ſtand and fall to. Charity hopeth all things.</hi> And I muſt tell you my Mind freely, for I have vow'd to follow <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> wherever they lead me: That I think it had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and more like Chriſtians, if no Member of either Church had medled with the Events of things, and leapt into God's Judgment-Seat, and pronounc'd final Sentence upon Souls. That certainly being a Secret and Prerogative peculiar to <hi>God,</hi> who only is <hi>the Searcher of Mens Hearts,</hi> knows all things, and has an abſolute Dominion over his Creatures, and can do all that his Juſtice, his Goodneſs, and his Mercy <hi>Wills.</hi> Had the Paſtors of each Church done no more, but barely and plainly taught the Truths of <hi>God,</hi> or what they ſincerely believ'd to be ſo, and left the Judgment of Perſons to him, that always <hi>judgeth right;</hi> they had doubtleſs done their Duty. But 'tis evident the Men of your Church <hi>firſt</hi> us'd it to work upon Mens Paſſions, and what they could not perſuade their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings to for want of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to do it by frighting of them. For 'tis too apparent, that more are ſway'd by Fear than Love; more are drawn by their Affections and Paſſions, than by their Reaſon; and ſome of our Church-men to countermine your Policy, found it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to imitate you, as far as Truth and Chriſtian Charity would permit them. And this may ſuffice alſo to apologize for my uſing it in my <hi>Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It now remains, Sir, that I ſpeak to another thing which ſeem'd to diſturb you; which is, Whether I am a <hi>Lay-man,</hi> or a <hi>Clergy-man.</hi> For I find you wavering about it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107793:6"/>I'll endeavour to fix you, tho in a doubtful caſe; Why ſhould not Charity have inclin'd you that brag of ſo much, to believe me when I profeſs my ſelf a <hi>Lay-man?</hi> Well, but <hi>I ſpeak ſo like a Clergy-man, ſo almoſt in the very Words and Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of a Doctor of my Church, and another Doctor mention'd</hi> in your <hi>Laſt Reply, that you cannot but take what I ſay for Church-Sence, dropping through a Lay-Pen.</hi> Sir, I muſt needs thank you for the Honour you do me, in <hi>taking</hi> me to ſpeak like ſuch great Men; but I have not Vanity enough to believe that I do. Yet thus much I'll confeſs, that I deſire to live no longer than I can, if not ſpeak, yet love and admire the Church-of-<hi>England Sence.</hi> But is it impoſſible for a <hi>Lay-man</hi> to ſpeak like a <hi>Clergy-man?</hi> Does Holy Orders make ſuch a difference? Or do you imagine I have never read any of our Churches Writers? Why may not then my Mind be tinctured by them? And ſo what I ſpeak or write, bear ſome reſemblance to them? Is there not many a Son like his Father? And how do you know but I am the Son of a Clergy-man? and ſo by Blood de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive ſomething of their way of Writing. But to make an end; I fancy, Sir, that you, or whoever was the Author of the <hi>Firſt Part of the Papiſt Miſrepreſented, &amp;c.</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of your Church, have found to your grief and ſhame, that either of theſe Doctors you ſpeak of, could if they had pleas'd to have undertaken ſo mean a work, have writ ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of a <hi>Preface,</hi> than I have done, to the diſadvantage of the <hi>French</hi> Popery now imitated in <hi>England.</hi> Let the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the performance prevail over you, to believe that neither of them made it. But indeed you are <hi>Injurious</hi> to them, to fancy they would be guilty of ſuch indirect dealing. No, No, Sir, the Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have a better Cauſe, they need uſe no Arts, or Tricks, no feign'd Miracles, no bold Untruths, no malicious Whiſpers and Slanders to ſupport and defend it, nor put Shams upon the World. This practice is none of theirs; and if you pleaſe that may be added, as a mark to prove ours a <hi>true</hi> Church: And indeed I could eaſily perſuade my ſelf to believe, that your own practice, &amp; that of your Party was in your Thoughts, when this Fancy entred into your Brain. But in a Word, and to put you out of pain about theſe two Doctors (for I cannot blame you for dreading them) I do aſſure you that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107793:7"/>neither of them made that <hi>Preface;</hi> and once more, that I who now write this Letter to you am a <hi>Lay-man,</hi> and writ that <hi>Preface,</hi> ſuch as 'tis. And if I could but be <hi>infallibly</hi> certain, that the <hi>old</hi> Popery was alter'd in the point of Malice, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and ſeeking occaſion againſt thoſe who never ſo little oppoſe or hinder the deſigns of <hi>Rome,</hi> I would give you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire ſatisfaction in this Particular, and not only tell you my Name, but where I live. But becauſe I cannot get out of my Thoughts ſome late Actions, and that hard uſage of the brave Author of <hi>Wholſome Advices, &amp;c.</hi> I fear leſt <hi>Old</hi> Popery may be practis'd upon me too; and therefore think it but common Prudence to conceal my ſelf: For, to tell you true, I am not yet weary of that little Happineſs I enjoy.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, you make <hi>your</hi> Miſrepreſenter tell the World, that I am <hi>dabling out of my Element;</hi> by which one would think, that after all, you believ'd I am a Layman. Well, but how out of my Element? May not a Layman tell Truth, and do good to his Neighbour's Soul? Is God's Spirit, is all Knowledg limited to Holy Orders? Becauſe there are ſome Functions appropriated to <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> ſuch as Adminiſtring the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> does it therefore follow, that a Layman may neither write nor diſcourſe of any Matters of Religion? Pray, Sir, does that Command, <hi>Thou ſhalt love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf,</hi> oblige <hi>Laymen</hi> as well as <hi>Clergymen?</hi> If it does, and ſince I may edify my ſelf, why, I beſeech you, not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? And can a Man expreſs his Charity to his Neighbour in a higher manner than in Spiritual Things? But the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are infinite which might be us'd in this Caſe. And therefore I ſhall only ask you whether <hi>Tertullian</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> and many other of the Ancient Fathers, writ not about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion when they were Laymen? Nay, more; did not Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> and Pope <hi>Nicholas,</hi> admit <hi>Laymen</hi> into Councils? And, pray, what was <hi>Picus Mirandula,</hi> but an Earl, and meer Layman? and Sir <hi>Thomas More</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>England?</hi> But above all, what was that Prince who wrote againſt <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> for which the Pope thought fit to beſtow the Title of <hi>Defender of the Faith</hi> upon him? But indeed why ſhould it ſeem ſtrange, that you and your Church ſhould find fault with Laymen's medling in Controverſies of <hi>Religion,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally againſt you, when you dare totally barr Laymens <hi>read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:107793:7"/>the Holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> for which they have a Command from God, <hi>Search the Scriptures;</hi> and perſwade them to put out their Eyes, and throw away their Reaſon, which <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> has given them to be their Guide through this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful World. And yet I dare ſay, that if a <hi>Layman</hi> would undertake ſo <hi>knotty</hi> a piece of Work, as to write in Defence of your Church, that you would not tell him that he was <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ling out of his Element,</hi> tho he were no better than a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligate Poet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I paſs over your unhandſom Language, and 'tis below me to return it. But I cannot but ſtand amaz'd, to find a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and a maintainer of the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> make <hi>his</hi> Miſrepreſenter ſay, That the Proteſtant Teachers <hi>know the People they have to deal with—that their diſcerning Faculties are ſtupified—that they'l paſs over fifty Contradictions, without once ſtumbling; and that there's no fear of enquiring, How can this be?</hi> No, Sir, the Teachers of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are not guilty of this Tyranny. We are Members of a Church that invites all her Children to the higheſt attainment of Knowledg, and teaches them that a <hi>reaſonable Service</hi> is the moſt acceptable to God; and impoſes nothing upon them, that either deſtroys or contradicts their Reaſon and Senſes; that not only allows her Children to read the Holy Scriptures, but beſeeches them to do it, provided they do it with a modeſt dependence on their <hi>lawful</hi> Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for the ſenſe of <hi>ſome</hi> Texts; which may not be ſo clear to Perſons who are unacquainted with the Proprieties of the Languages in which the Holy Scriptures were writ, and the Cuſtoms and Manners of the People and Countries where they were pen'd. In a word, the Church of <hi>England</hi> allows a private Liberty of examining all things ſhe propounds, and does not expect that Men ſhould follow her blindfold. She requires indeed Obedience in thoſe <hi>few</hi> Points which are <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely</hi> neceſſary to Salvation, becauſe they are ſo plain, that it is impoſſible for an honeſt and ſound Mind to queſtion them: But for things of an indifferent Nature, ſhe only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that for the ſake of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Order</hi> and <hi>Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> that her Children would not diſpute about them. In line, ſhe is very ſure, that <hi>they</hi> and they <hi>only,</hi> are her <hi>true</hi> Children, her moſt <hi>ſincere</hi> Members, who are the moſt obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107793:8"/>to <hi>Scripture,</hi> and moſt ready to yield to the Evidence of <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Senſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, Sir, I have endeavour'd to reſtore Peace to your Mind, by ſhewing that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are not at all uncharitable, but that Papiſts are; and that I am a Layman, and yet may meddle in Divinity, and not be <hi>dabling out of my Element.</hi> And now I hope you'l be no longer in a fright of thoſe two Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors you hinted; for, aſſure your ſelf, that unleſs there be occaſion to defend a poor <hi>Layman</hi> of their Church, as far as the Truth and the Religion of it are concern'd (for you may poſſibly hear from me upon ſome other Point) theſe two Doctors are better employ'd, than to trouble themſelves with you.</p>
            <p>But if againſt this plain Proof, that the Papiſts are the <hi>only</hi> uncharitable Perſons, you will yet rub your Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and make <hi>Proteſtants</hi> as bad, What Remedy? Truth will be Truth ſtill. And however it fares with us, we have over and above this Satisfaction; and you know the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of an Enemy proves much, that <hi>to give us our due,</hi> you ſay, we <hi>are the moſt gentile and courtly Damners</hi> that can poſſibly be met with. Now for the Reward of this frank Acknowledgment, I wiſh with all my Soul, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> could ſay ſo much of <hi>Papiſts.</hi> But the continual ſound of <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Hereticks, Damn'd Schiſmaticks,</hi> and ſuch rude and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Names every where heard, will not poſſibly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them.</p>
            <p>To conclude all; I ſhall only deſire you, for prevention of more trouble than needs be, (and I have known a great Controverſy to ariſe from a Matter leſs liable to Miſtake) to take notice, that the very Point in Difference, is not, Whether the Religion of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> or <hi>Papiſts</hi> is the Trueſt or Safeſt? For he that believes the ſecond Commandment was given by God, and that it is not lawful to worſhip any <hi>Being</hi> but only <hi>God,</hi> who gave <hi>being</hi> to all Things, need not be to ſeek in that: Neither is it, whether the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> or Papiſts are the <hi>moſt</hi> uncharitable? But, in Truth, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Queſtion is, Whether the Papiſts are not the <hi>only</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Perſons? And I think I have fully prov'd that that they are ſo, even from the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:107793:8"/>
            <p>Sir, I heartily wiſh you and your Party would, before it be too late, ſhew ſo much Charity to your ſelves and others, to leave off deceiving the poor Souls, and diſturbing the Peace of Mankind, tho by ſucceeding in your Enterprize, you might arrive to the higheſt Temporal Felicities, and by deſiſting, ſuffer the greateſt of Humane Miſeries.</p>
            <closer>And I am, <signed>Your very humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A POSTSCRIPT by the Author of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the last Reply of the <hi>Repreſenter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving leave to fill up this place, I uſe it to rectify an Error in the 119th Page of the laſt Anſwer to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter;</hi> where an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to <hi>Cochleus</hi> was omitted without correction, and ſo he is brought in for the Reporter of thoſe Famous Fictions about <hi>Luther</hi>'s Death; whereas his part in it is the leaſt, the reſt being reported by others, particularly by <hi>Pontacus, Lindan,</hi> and our Countryman <hi>W. Reinolds. Coch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leus</hi> himſelf, with the Epiſtle concerning <hi>Luther</hi>'s latter-end, publiſhed by him fol. 298 of his Hiſtory, tells the manner of his Death otherwiſe. But <hi>Thyraeus</hi> a Jeſuit was the Man whom I had in my mind, for contradicting thoſe with whom he agreed in the general Deſign of Defamation. For he ſays, <hi>That day when</hi> Luther <hi>died, thoſe poſſeſſed perſons in a Town of</hi> Brabant <hi>(where there were very many) who expected deliverance by the Patronage of St.</hi> Dymna <hi>(of which for many years many had experience) were delivered from the Devils, and a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were again poſſeſſed. For the Caſe was this; that the cruel Spirits again tormenting thoſe miſerable perſons, being asked where they had bestowed themſelves the day before? anſwered, That by the Command of their Chief they were called forth to the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the New Prophet, and their faithful Fellow-worker,</hi> Luther, <hi>and had been preſent at it. Which matter was confirmed by a Servant of</hi> Luther, <hi>who was with him while he was dying miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107793:9"/>For as he was looking out of the Caſement for freſh Air, he was greatly affrighted to ſee more than once I know not how many black ugly Spirits skipping and dancing not far off. And this alſo was confirmed by the Crows, which with a fearful noiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied the Body of</hi> Luther <hi>as it was carried to</hi> Wittemberg. Which wiſe Tale (<hi>De Demoniacis par.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 99.) is alſo abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Flor. Rainundus de orig. Haereſ.</hi> l. 3. p. 40. but does by no means agree with what <hi>Reinolds</hi> reports in his <hi>Calvino-Turciſmus, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 957, that <hi>Luther,</hi> after a merry Supper, was in the Night ſuddenly ſtrangled by his Wife. This Buſineſs, as they have ſeverally reported it, is a very no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Inſtance how early they began the Trade of <hi>Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting matters of Fact.</hi> But more of this when there is more occaſion.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add, that the Authority I have for ſaying that they ſpread ſuch like lewd Stories of <hi>Luther</hi>'s Death before he was dead, is indeed the Authority of Proteſtant Writers, and chiefly of <hi>Phil. Lonicerus</hi> in his <hi>Theatrum Historicum,</hi> nor could it be expected that we ſhould have any other.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107793:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107793:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
